A Guide to the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1838-1987
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series 1: Literary Manuscripts
  - "Is Walt Whitman's Poetry Poetical?" [ca.1874], AMs, 8 pp. on 8 l., handwritten, 25 cm. x 19.5 cm., with typed transcription, Barrow. #3829 (Bowers #23). (Box-folder 1:47)
    Walt Whitman's response to criticism from The Nation, mailed to John Burroughs whom Walt Whitman asks to edit the MS and submit it under his own name. Consists of 8 leaves written in ink, pasted to archival paper, and bound together with string. Transcription of letter from Walt Whitman to John Burroughs reads: Dear John Burroughs, I enclose you an article from the Nation of Jan. 29. How will the MS. article I have scratched off do in the main as an answer to it? (to help keep the pot a-boiling.) Do you feel like making up an article out of said MS—adding or excising what you see fit—signing your name to it—and sending to the Nation man?
  - "Last of the War Cases," [1863 October 13], AMs, 2 pp. on 2 l., Barrow. #3829-h. (Box-folder 1:48)
  - Leaves of Grass, [ca. 1855-1856], AMs, 12 fragments on 7 leaves, #3829. (Bowers #20). (Box-folder 1:49)
    These notes, inscribed on scraps of paper of diverse types and sizes, went into the making of a number of poems used in Leaves of Grass, although some of them never seem to have been used, and some are prose notes. In several cases a collector has pasted two or more leaves to the same sheet of more contemporary paper, but for convenience and accuracy the leaves are described individually here.
    - Fragment 1: After death, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 7 x 15 cm.
      On a small section of light yellow wove paper (7 x 15 cm.) with all four corners cropped for mounting. Four pinholes appear in the center. Inscribed and revised on the recto in pencil; the first line on the verso (beginning "I have all lives, all effects, all/ causes,...") is inscribed and revised in the same brown ink as Leaf 2, and the two lines that follow it (beginning "This is the earth's word—the round/ and compact earth's,") are inscribed, revised, and deleted (with a single vertical stroke) in pencil. Bucke prints both sets of lines on p. 32 of Notes and Fragments. Whitman apparently never used the recto lines, but the deleted lines on the verso bear a strong resemblance to the opening of his 1856 Poem of The Sayers of The Words of The Earth, titled in successive editions (as Bradley and Blodgett note) To the Sayers of Words (1860 and 1867), Carol of Words (1871, 1876), and, finally (in the 1881 edition of Leaves ), A Song of the Rolling Earth. The undeleted ink line on the verso is a later(?) draft of a line inscribed in Feinberg notebook #697 at the Library of Congress, transcribed by Blodgett in Walt Whitman: An 1855-56 Notebook Toward the Second Edition of "Leaves of Grass" (1956) and reprinted in his and Bradley's Comprehensive Reader's Edition of Leaves.
    - Fragment 2: As to you, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 7 x 15.5 cm.
      On a small section of the same light yellow wove paper as Leaf 1, cut and cropped irregularly down to 7 x 15.5 cm. Multiple pinholes appear in the center. This section was evidently pasted to and then pulled away from another page; some fragments of that other page remain affixed to the top. Beneath them can be discerned the ink number 2. In the upper left corner appears an "X" within parentheses, which was formerly covered by the other page. Inscribed in the same brown ink as the undeleted line on the verso of Leaf 1; revised in that ink and in pencil. Whitman apparently never used this poem or fragment, but Bucke prints it (combined with other verses) on p. 29 of Notes and Fragments.
    - Fragment 3: Poem of, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 4 x 8 cm.
      On a very small section of tan wove paper (4 x 8 cm.). All four corners are cropped for mounting. What seems to be a pinhole appears in the upper right corner. Inscribed in brown ink with no revisions. These notes, along with those on Leaves 4 and 5, could have represented an early stage of a number of poems. One possibility is poem 18 in the Calamus cluster, new to the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass. This poem was permanently retitled City of Orgies in 1867 (see Leaf 4). Bucke prints the notes on p. 171 with an ellipses not present in the manuscript, and they are republished with the note "Manuscript not found" on p. 1372 of Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts (vol. 4).
    - Fragment 4: A City Walk, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 4.5 x 12 cm.
      On a very small section of uncropped white wove paper (4.5 x 12 cm.). No pinholes. Inscribed (hurriedly) in black ink using a thin nib. A bright pinkish-red ink check mark(?) appears in the upper right corner of the note. A faint horizontal line beneath part of "A City Walk," along with the words' capitalization and central position on the page, indicate that Whitman may have contemplated using the words as the title of an independent poem. The closest he came to this title was City of Walks and Joys, the name he originally assigned to Calamus 18 in his Blue Book revisions of the 1860 edition of Leaves. This title was changed in the Blue Book to City of orgies, walks and joys and finally became City of Orgies in the 1867 edition. These notes, written in the form of a single poetic verse, could represent an intermediate stage between the notes on Leaf 3 and those on Leaf 5. Bucke prints the lines in prose form on p. 120 of Notes and Fragments. Bucke's transcription is republished, accompanied by the note "Manuscript not found," on p. 1292 of the Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts (vol. 4).
    - Fragment 5. Walks Down This Street; The Houses Duly Numbered., ca. 1856, 1 leaf, handwritten, 7 x 16 cm. paster to 4 x 15.5 cm.
      On a composite leaf comprising two sections of white wove paper (7 x 16 and 4 x 15.5 cm.) pasted together. The majority of the eight corners are cropped for mounting; the upper section was apparently cropped before being pasted to the lower section. Inscribed in dark brown-black ink with no revisions. The trial verses on the lower section (beginning "Poem—As of walking along a street") are fragmentary and hurriedly inscribed, but the upper section is written in ornamental script, and both parts of the title are underlined. A wavy line appears at the foot of that section. The word "Original" at the head of the upper section suggests that Whitman was sketching out a new poem for a revised edition of Leaves of Grass. If it was the 1860 edition, as his style of inscription here appears to indicate, it is possible that this leaf, like Leaves 3 and 4, could represent an early stage of the poem that would eventually become City of Orgies. Bucke prints the lower set of notes on p. 45 of Notes and Fragments.
    - Fragment 6. Europe ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 16 x 14 cm.
      On a section of off-white wove paper (16 x 14 cm.) with all four corners cropped for mounting. Many pinholes cluster to the left of the center of the page. Inscribed and revised on both sides in pencil. The lines on the verso are deleted with a single vertical pencil stroke. They originally occupied the lower half of a full leaf of verse; after deleting these (current) verso lines and discarding the upper half of the leaf Whitman turned the page ninety degrees and flipped it over to use for the current recto notes. The recto notes represent an early stage of lines partially incorporated in Poem of Salutation, the new third poem in the 1856 edition of Leaves of Grass, which was permanently retitled Salut au Monde! in the 1860 edition. If the note or title "Europe" suggests that Whitman might have first intended to divide his salutations into discrete sections based on the different continents, this is a plan he did not follow in the published version(s). The more polished (but deleted) lines on the verso represent a recasting in poetic form of several lines from the 1855 Preface to Leaves. These were further revised for the 1856 Poem of Many in One, after which the first verse drafted on this page (cut off here, and beginning "over the Texan, Mexican, Florid[ian,]/ Cuban seas...") was dropped. The two verses below this, however, were preserved relatively unchanged through the poem's many transformations until the text was essentially fixed under the title By Blue Ontario's Shore in 1881. Bucke prints the top section of notes (incorrectly) on p. 157, and the lower section of verses (beginning "And the tough Scotch sailor crosses the Minch...") on p. 10 of Notes and Fragments. On p. 1980 of the Notes and Unpublished Manuscripts (vol. 5) Grier reports that this manuscript has not been found.
    - Fragment 7. And as the shores of the sea I live near and love are to me, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 13 x 14 cm.
      On one section of thick white wove paper (13 x 14.5 cm.) apparently taken from a sheet used for trial printings of a book engraving; a plate mark can be clearly seen on the verso. The lower corners are cropped for mounting. Multiple pinholes in center. Inscribed and revised in pencil. Like the contents of Leaf 6, these two verses represent a draft (possibly a slightly later one than Leaf 6) of lines that would be further revised and incorporated in the new 1856 poem Poem of Salutation, permanently retitled Salut au Monde! in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass. The second line (beginning "And as the mountains of my land/ are to me..."), greatly expanded, would become lines 49-54 (section 4) of Salut au Monde! in Bradley and Blodgett's edition of the poem, and the first line seems to have been expanded even more in that section's description of the oceans of the world. Bucke transcribes the leaf on p. 11.
    - Fragment 8. Poem of Pictures, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 6.5 x 15.5 cm.
      On a small section of white wove paper irregularly cut down to 6.5 x 15.5 cm. Inscribed and revised in dark brown ink. A phrase beginning "Picture of one of/ the Greek games" appears in the upper right corner, delimited from the rest of the notes with two curved lines. The words "Spanish bull fight" appear in their own semicircle (damaged by Whitman's cutting) in the lower right corner. Bucke transcribes the notes on p. 177, and Grier (p. 1294, vol. 4) republishes them, describing the manuscript as "not found." To build on Grier's notes, the lines seem to occupy a middle space between the very early notebook poem Pictures and the 1856 Poem of Salutation (ultimately Salut au Monde! ).
    - Fragment 9. My two theses, ca. 1856, 1 leaf, handwritten, 4 x 16 cm. pasted to 10.5 x 16 cm.
      On a small composite leaf of white wove paper, ruled in blue on one side, formed by pasting a section (4 x 16 cm.) containing one line of notes (beginning "runs through all the poems...") below the set of notes transcribed above, which were written on a section measuring 10.5 x 16 cm. Multiple pinholes in both sections. Both sections are inscribed in pencil, with one revision in black ink. Bucke transcribes these notes on p. 167 of Notes and Fragments, and Grier republishes them (with the note "Manuscript not found") on p. 383 of the Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts (vol. 1).
    - Fragment 10. The circus boy is riding in the, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 10.5 x 14 cm.
      On a section of off-white wove paper (10.5 x 14 cm.). Multiple pinholes cluster towards the top of the page. Inscribed and revised on both sides in pencil. The lines on the verso are deleted with a single vertical pencil stroke. Those on the recto are separated by a horizontal line. The verso lines (beginning with the individually deleted line "O Walt Whitman, show us some/ pictures!" and continuing "America, always Pictorial!") represent a later draft of the beginning of the poem Pictures than the most complete extant version, which is contained in the pre-1855 Pictures notebook currently housed at Yale University. Bucke dates the lines to around 1880, when Whitman was working on a short version of Pictures both for magazine publication and for the 1881 edition of Leaves, where it was published as My Picture-Gallery. (See the entry for My picture gallery below.) But Whitman's early style of inscription in this draft, along with the line "It is round—it has room for America, north and south" and his use of his own name in the deleted first line, all suggest that Whitman may have inscribed this draft around the same time that he was working on the new 1856 Poem of Salutations (eventually Salut au Monde! ). This draft also suggests that at one point he may have considered linking what would become Poem of Salutations and the formally and thematically similar Pictures more directly. Bucke prints the verso and recto lines, with several deleted words restored, on p. 27 of Notes and Fragments.
    - Fragment 11. How can there be immortality, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 4.5 x 14.5 cm.
      On a very small section of white laid paper cut and cropped irregularly down to 4.5 x 14.5 cm. Multiple pinholes run up the center of the section. The recto lines are inscribed and heavily revised in brown ink, and deleted (en masse) with a single vertical pencil stroke. Along the lower edge can be seen the tops of words discarded after cutting. These trial verses bear a strong resemblance to the (eventual) second verse paragraph in section 6 of Starting from Paumanok, first published in 1860 as Proto-Leaf. Bradley and Blodgett note other relationships to the fragment The Body—, published on p. 37-8 of Notes and Fragments and housed at Duke University, and to the poems that would eventually become Song of Myself and I Sing the Body Electric. The fragmentary lines on the verso (beginning "Downward, buoyant, swif[t]"), which are inscribed and revised in pencil, represent a different version of a line incorporated in the pre-1855 notebook poem Pictures and of one inscribed in the 1854 notebook [I know a rich capitalist...], currently housed at the New York Public Library. Bucke prints incomplete transcriptions of the contents of both sides of Leaf 11 on p. 38 of Notes and Fragments, and presents a different version of the recto lines (transcribed from the same manuscript?) on p. 48. Bradley and Blodgett's new transcription, under the title [Divine Is the Person], appears on p. 602 of the expanded and revised edition of the Comprehensive Reader's Edition of Leaves.
    - Fragment 12. Pure water, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 16 x 13 cm.
      On a section of light yellow wove paper (16 x 13 cm.) with all four corners cropped for mounting. Four pinholes appear in the center. Inscribed and revised in pencil. Below these trial verses, separated from them by a diagonal pencil stroke, appears a cartoon hand pointing to the annotation "I must have/ Poem[.]" Bucke prints the verses (without the prose note) on p. 49 of Notes and Fragments.
  - "Leaves of Grass," 1857-1871, 230 leaves, handwritten (Bowers #31). (Folders 50-51)
    These descriptions follow the present arbitrary but longstanding physical arrangement of the manuscripts, first collected in a series of folders, and now in two boxed binders. This arrangement groups manuscripts according to their position in and out of the "clusters" comprising the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass, although the 1860 order of the clusters themselves has not been followed by the collector who arranged the poems. Sparkles from the Wheel and Fables (both 1871; see [Vol. 2, p. 163] and [Vol. 2, p. 164]) are included in the list by virtue of being housed with earlier poems in the second binder.
    All of these poems except for Sparkles from the Wheel and Fables were published in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass. The manuscripts are generally followed by print versions of the poems disbound by a collector from the 1860 edition. Since Whitman apparently had no contact with the printed pages they have not been described here. Neither have the annotations made by collectors on many of Whitman's leaves. The measurements given below are taken at the points of greatest height and width, in that order, for each page. Following Fredson Bowers's practice in describing the manuscripts, the location of major pinhole clusters in each page, where present, has also been noted. (The pinholes, as Bowers argues, can yield helpful clues as to Whitman's practices of revision. Intact pages have multiple pinholes in the middle; thus, pinholes at the top of a small page indicate that the fragment was removed from the lower section of a full leaf, and vice versa). The types of paper and writing implements used by Whitman in each case have been documented for the same reasons. Since, in many cases, after 1860 Whitman changed the poems' titles and revised and transferred them elsewhere, a brief narrative of each poem's post-1860 evolution accompanies its description.
    The entry after the page numbers is the first autograph line at the top of the page. Beginning at page 34 of volume 1, the corresponding published poems are removed from 1860 edition and interleaved with the manuscripts.
    - Premonition, pages 1-33, Volume 1:
      On thirty-three leaves comprising four types of paper (in a variety of shapes and sizes): pink, blue wove, white wove, and light blue Williamsburgh (Brooklyn) tax forms—inscribed, Bowers argues, in that order. Each leaf is numbered consecutively by Whitman, in pencil, in the lower left corner. Each leaf is also stabbed in the left margin and punctured with numerous pinholes. Bowers has identified at least four stages of revision based on the writing implements and ink used by Whitman to make his corrections: first pencil, then dark ink with a fine pen, once again pencil, and finally thin light-brown ink. Premonition was published as the introductory poem to the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass under the title Proto-Leaf. In the 1867 and later editions it appeared directly after the opening Inscriptions cluster as Starting from Paumanok.
      - Page 1, Volume 1. "Premonition," 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 21.5 x 12 cm.
        On verso of light blue Williamsburgh tax form (21.5 x 12 cm.), in black ink, with corrections in the same ink and in pencil. Multiple pinholes in center. This is a revision of the fragment that appears at the top of Leaf 2, and corresponds to section 1 of Proto-Leaf in the 1860 edition.
      - Page 2, Volume 1. Mannahatta-boy of, 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 12 x 13 cm.
        On a small pink sheet (12 x 13 cm.), in original black ink, with extensive deletions and revisions in fine pen (black ink) and pencil. Pinholes near top. This seems to have been the original first leaf of Premonition. In drafting the revised version of this first section on a Williamsburgh tax form (see Vol. 1, p. 1) Whitman excised and apparently destroyed the verses at the top of this leaf, striking through the verses (beginning "[Boy of the] Mannahatta—boy of/ the prairies,...") below the cut. He then left a revised section of verses on the lower part of the leaf (beginning "Victory, union, faith, democracy,/ prudence,...") undeleted. These lines correspond to section 2 of Proto-Leaf.
      - Page 3, Volume 1. This then is life, 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 12 x 13 cm.
        On pink leaf (21 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with extensive revisions in fine pen, pencil, and light ink. Pinholes in the center. The three verse sections—beginning "This then is life," "How curious! How real!," and "Take my Leaves America! Make/ places..."—correspond to sections 3, 4, and 13 of Proto-Leaf.
      - Page 4, Volume 1. I returned to old times, 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 10.5 x 12 cm.
        On verso of light blue Williamsburgh tax form cut down to 10.5 x 12 cm., in black ink, with revisions in pencil and light ink. Pinholes in the center. A revision of lines deleted from the top of Leaf 5; corresponds to section 14 of Proto-Leaf.
      - Page 5, Volume 1. I do not discredit old times, 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 22 x 13 cm.
        On pink leaf (22 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with deletions and revisions in pencil and fine pen. Pinholes in center. Whitman struck through the section beginning "I do not discredit old times," the revised version of which appears on Leaf 4, and which corresponds to section 15 of Proto-Leaf. Below a horizontal line he left revised but undeleted the section beginning "Antiques of men," which corresponds to section 16 of Proto-Leaf.
      - Page 6, Volume 1. Here lands female and male, 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 21.5 x 13 cm.
        On a pink leaf (21.5 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with extensive revisions in medium fine pen, pencil, and fine pen to the first section, corresponding to section 17 of Proto-Leaf. Pinholes in center. In the next two sections—[The Soul!] and [I will make the poems of materials,...]—corresponding to sections 18 and 19 of Proto-Leaf, only minor revisions have been made, these in fine pen.
      - Page 7, Volume 1. I will make a song for these, 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 17 x 13 cm.
        On pink leaf cut down to 17 x 13 cm., in black ink, with revisions in pencil, medium fine pen, and light ink. Pinholes below center. Corresponds to section 20 of Proto-Leaf. The excised portion contained several verses and was moved to Leaf 8 (see Vol. 1, p. 8).
      - Page 8, Volume 1. I will be the preparer of what is, 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 17 x 13 cm.
        On a torn sheet of blue wove paper (17 x 13 cm.), with the excised portion from pink Leaf 7 (beginning "I will be the preparer of what is/ to come...") pasted to the foot of the leaf. Pinholes mostly in center of composite leaf. The pasted-on section became the first three verses of section 21 in Proto-Leaf. Whitman struck through six unaltered lines (beginning "I am the child of Democracy,") in light-brown ink on the upper portion of the original blue leaf; these, Bowers observes, represent an intermediate stage between verses on a leaf used for Enfans d'Adam and verses on Leaf 12 of Premonition (see Vol. 1, p. 47 and Vol. 1, p. 12). After appearing on Leaf 12, the verses—much altered from their earliest iteration on the Enfans d'Adam leaf—next became section 23 of the published Proto-Leaf.
      - Page 9, Volume 1. And employments! I will make, 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 11 x 13 cm.
        On pink leaf, cut down to 11 x 13 cm., written in black ink with no revisions. Pinhole clusters are located both at the foot of leaf, dating from before Whitman's cutting of it, and in the current center. The excised portion was renumbered Leaf 17 (see Vol. 1, p. 17). Leaf 9's remaining verses correspond to the second two verses of section 21 of Proto-Leaf.
      - Page 10, Volume 1. I will make the song of companionship, 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 16 x 13 cm.
        On blue wove page torn down to 16 x 13 cm. In light-brown ink, with extensive revisions in the same ink. Pinholes in center. Corresponds to the first six lines of section 22 of Proto-Leaf.
      - Page 11, Volume 1. I will make the new evangel, 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 9 x 13 cm.
        On blue wove page cut down to 9 x 13 cm., in light-brown ink with no revisions. Pinholes in the current center and at the foot of the page (the original center). Incision patterns indicate that the blank portion cut from the foot of the leaf was pasted to the back of Leaf 17 for reinforcement (see Vol. 1, p. 17). Corresponds to verses 7-9 of section 22 of Proto-Leaf.
      - Page 12, Volume 1. I am all credulous, 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 6.5 x 16.5 cm.